<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-22T17:24:22+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Robert Marsland</title><subtitle>Shams and delusions are esteemed for soundest truths, while reality is fabulous.</subtitle><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><entry><title type="html">Collective computation in biological populations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/collective-computation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collective computation in biological populations" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:07+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:07+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/collective-computation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/collective-computation"><![CDATA[<p>Ecosystems may seem unlikely substrates for sophisticated computation. But two key features make them a promising way for solving sophisticated machine learning problems based on constrained optimization. First of all, self-replication provides stable constraint enforcement. Stable coexistence requires that the environmental state satisfy a precise set of conditions, such that the population growth rates of all species are simultaneously zero. A slight deviation from this constraint will lead to exponential growth or decay of one or more population sizes, which in turn will modify the environment until these conditions are restored. Secondly, distributing the computation over a whole ecosystem provides automatic parallelization, which becomes particularly important for solving problems efficiently in high dimension.</p>

<p>This intuition can be transformed into a precise mathematical duality, as my coauthors and I have recently shown <a class="citation" href="#mehta2019constrained">(Mehta et al., 2019)</a>. The duality opens some interesting horizons for thinking about ecosystems and about classic machine learning problems, suggesting new observables for field ecologists <a class="citation" href="#marsland2019minimum">(Marsland III et al., 2020)</a> and new algorithms for online learning <a class="citation" href="#howell2019machine">(Howell et al., 2020)</a>.</p>

<p>But is it possible to actually use an ecosystem to perform a computation? The adaptive immune system is a natural place to start. T cells are clearly performing a collective computation to determine whether a given antigen comes from a native protein or from a pathogen. My colleagues and I have recently developed a model of immune self-tolerance that sheds new light on the nature of this computation <a class="citation" href="#marsland2021tregs">(Marsland III et al., 2021)</a>.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="mehta2019constrained">Mehta, P., Cui, W., Wang, C.-H., &amp; Marsland III, R. (2019). Constrained optimization as ecological dynamics with applications to random quadratic programming in high dimensions. <i>Physical Review E</i>, <i>99</i>(5), 052111.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.aps.org/pre/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevE.99.052111"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_mehta2019constrained-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.04221"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_mehta2019constrained-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/mehta2019constrained.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2019minimum">Marsland III, R., Cui, W., &amp; Mehta, P. (2020). The minimum environmental perturbation principle: A new perspective on niche theory. <i>The American Naturalist</i>, <i>196</i>.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/710093"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019minimum-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09673"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019minimum-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019minimum.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019minimum.zip"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--supplement" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">Supplement</button></a>
    </li>
<li><span id="howell2019machine">Howell, O., Wenping, C., Marsland III, R., &amp; Mehta, P. (2020). Machine Learning as Ecology. <i>Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical</i>, <i>53</i>, 334001.</span>

    
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1751-8121/ab956e"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_howell2019machine-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.00868"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_howell2019machine-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/howell2019machine.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2021tregs">Marsland III, R., Howell, O., Mayer, A., &amp; Mehta, P. (2021). Tregs self-organize into a computing ecosystem and implement a sophisticated optimization algorithm for mediating immune response. <i>PNAS</i>, <i>118</i>, e2011709118.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/1/e2011709118.short"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2021tregs-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00252"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2021tregs-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    
    

    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ecosystems may seem unlikely substrates for sophisticated computation. But two key features make them a promising way for solving sophisticated machine learning problems based on constrained optimization. First of all, self-replication provides stable constraint enforcement. Stable coexistence requires that the environmental state satisfy a precise set of conditions, such that the population growth rates of all species are simultaneously zero. A slight deviation from this constraint will lead to exponential growth or decay of one or more population sizes, which in turn will modify the environment until these conditions are restored. Secondly, distributing the computation over a whole ecosystem provides automatic parallelization, which becomes particularly important for solving problems efficiently in high dimension.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Statistical physics approaches to community ecology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/typical-ecology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Statistical physics approaches to community ecology" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:06+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:06+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/typical-ecology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/typical-ecology"><![CDATA[<p>Microbial ecosystems manifest one of the main technical obstacles to predictive modeling of biological systems, which arises from their extreme heterogeneity. The standard methods of statistical mechanics produce powerful and robust predictions about the behavior of large collections of functionally identical particles, which are easily extended to mixtures of a few different kinds of components. But in most biological systems, the number of distinct types of components is unmanageably large, whether we are considering the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_genome">20,000 different genes in the human genome</a>, or the <a href="https://www.genome.jp/kegg/docs/statistics.html">20,000 distinct metabolites</a> involved in biochemical networks. Microbial ecosystems reproduce this same difficulty on a bigger length scale, with hundreds to thousands of coexisting “species” in a given natural community. The development of inexpensive DNA sequencing has made these systems an attractive setting for developing and testing new theoretical methods for overcoming this hurdle. Highly diverse microbial communities can be readily found on any plant leaf, pond droplet, or grain of soil, and sequencing technology makes it possible to determine which species are present there and in what abundance.</p>

<p>My colleagues and I have been adapting <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1742-5468/aab04e/meta">methods from the physics of disordered materials</a> to this new setting, deriving predictions about the diversity, composition and sensitivity of heterogeneous communities based on summary statistics about consumption preferences and byproduct secretion in the regional species pool. The key assumption behind these methods is that the parameters characterizing each species can be modeled as independent random variables drawn from a given probability distribution. This seems like an extreme assumption, given how much specific structure is already known about microbial behavior. But we have shown that at sufficiently high levels of diversity, the strong interactions between specific pairs of organisms based on known mechanisms can be overwhelmed by the sheer number of weak, uncharacterized interactions with all the other species in the system <a class="citation" href="#cui2019diverse">(Cui et al., 2021)</a>.</p>

<p>To check our calculations and facilitate hypothesis generation, I have also been developing <a href="https://github.com/Emergent-Behaviors-in-Biology/community-simulator">a Python package</a> for rapidly simulating diverse microbial ecosystems with randomly sampled parameters <a class="citation" href="#marsland2019community">(Marsland III et al., 2020)</a>. Using this package, I have shown that the robust patterns observed in large-scale surveys of microbial diversity (such as the Human Microbiome Project and Earth Microbiome Project) reflect the “typical” structure of diverse communities <a class="citation" href="#marsland2019minimal">(Marsland III et al., 2020)</a>.</p>

<p>I have also used this software to study some novel ecological phenomena that can arise in self-sufficient microbial ecosystems <a class="citation" href="#marsland2019available">(Marsland III et al., 2019)</a>. Since microbes generically produce usable byproducts whenever they consume an energy source, they can autonomously generate a complex chemical environment that supports a diverse community even when only a single energy source is supplied externally. This differs from the standard case considered in macroscopic ecology, where environmental conditions are either fixed or modified only through consumption. By performing simulations of this extreme case of a fully self-generated environment, I identified a transition in community structure as a function of the supply rate of the externally provided resource. At high supply rates, the community-level metabolic network percolates, and all possible byproducts are produced at sufficiently high concentrations to significantly contribute to the growth of some set of species. The scaling of diversity with the number of supplied resources in this regime agrees with analytic predictions obtained for “typical” communities. But at low supply rates, only species that directly consume the externally supplied resource can survive, and the resulting low-diversity state no longer satisfies the assumptions for calculating “typical” community properties.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="cui2019diverse">Cui, W., Marsland III, R., &amp; Mehta, P. (2021). Diverse communities behave like typical random ecosystems. <i>Physical Review E</i>, <i>104</i>, 034416.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.aps.org/pre/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevE.104.034416"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_cui2019diverse-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02610"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_cui2019diverse-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2019community">Marsland III, R., Cui, W., Goldford, J., &amp; Mehta, P. (2020). The Community Simulator: A Python package for microbial ecology. <i>PLoS ONE</i>, <i>15</i>, e0230430.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0230430"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019community-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.09367"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019community-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019community.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2019minimal">Marsland III, R., Cui, W., &amp; Mehta, P. (2020). A minimal model for microbial biodiversity can reproduce experimentally observed ecological patterns. <i>Scientific Reports</i>, <i>10</i>, 3308.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-60130-2"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019minimal-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.12914"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019minimal-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019minimal.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2019available">Marsland III, R., Cui, W., Goldford, J., Sanchez, A., Korolev, K., &amp; Mehta, P. (2019). Available energy fluxes drive a transition in the diversity, stability, and functional structure of microbial communities. <i>PLoS Computational Biology</i>, <i>15</i>(2), e1006793.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006793"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019available-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.12516"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019available-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019available.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2019available.zip"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--supplement" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">Supplement</button></a>
    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Microbial ecosystems manifest one of the main technical obstacles to predictive modeling of biological systems, which arises from their extreme heterogeneity. The standard methods of statistical mechanics produce powerful and robust predictions about the behavior of large collections of functionally identical particles, which are easily extended to mixtures of a few different kinds of components. But in most biological systems, the number of distinct types of components is unmanageably large, whether we are considering the 20,000 different genes in the human genome, or the 20,000 distinct metabolites involved in biochemical networks. Microbial ecosystems reproduce this same difficulty on a bigger length scale, with hundreds to thousands of coexisting “species” in a given natural community. The development of inexpensive DNA sequencing has made these systems an attractive setting for developing and testing new theoretical methods for overcoming this hurdle. Highly diverse microbial communities can be readily found on any plant leaf, pond droplet, or grain of soil, and sequencing technology makes it possible to determine which species are present there and in what abundance.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools for quantitative prediction in microbial communities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/microbiome-observables" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools for quantitative prediction in microbial communities" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:05+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:05+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/microbiome-observables</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/microbiome-observables"><![CDATA[<p>The concept of a “species” is notoriously ill-defined in the microbial realm. Instead of the sharp distinctions between different kinds of plants and animals we find in the macroscopic world, microbes manifest a fuzzier continuum of phenotypes. Given this blurriness, it should come as no surprise that it is difficult to predict “species”-level composition of microbial communities. But natural microbial communities do have sufficiently stable functional properties to be effectively utilized by macroscopic organisms to accomplish definite tasks. This means that there should be some community-level quantities that are reproducible and controllable, and some “relevant variables” that reliably control them, but what these quantities could be remains an open question.</p>

<p>I have recently been following up on an <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/205831v1.abstract">observation by some of my colleagues</a> that the composition of communities grown on single carbon sources is reproducible at a sufficiently high taxonomic level. Specifically, the family-level structure of the communities is sensitive to the choice of carbon source, but is strongly conserved for different communities, sampled from different field sites, when grown on the same carbon source. My first goal was to identify the chemical features of the carbon source that determine the community structure, using standard machine learning algorithms to predict community composition on novel carbon sources based on chemical similarity, and comparing these predictions with the measurements performed by my collaborators.</p>

<p>The next step would be to develop a method for inferring reproducible observables directly from the data, instead of using the historically contingent family groupings (which turn out not to generate reproducible measurements in other experimental settings). <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1504.02550">An interesting theoretical procedure</a> for this was proposed some time ago, using the eigenvectors of an individual-level, environment-specific interaction matrix. It is currently impossible to measure the entries of this matrix directly, and so practical implementation of this program requires a controlled procedure for estimating the matrix from the data. I have made some progress towards developing such a procedure, applying it to my collaborators’ data, and exploring other ways of obtaining meaningful functional groupings from the inferred matrix.</p>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The concept of a “species” is notoriously ill-defined in the microbial realm. Instead of the sharp distinctions between different kinds of plants and animals we find in the macroscopic world, microbes manifest a fuzzier continuum of phenotypes. Given this blurriness, it should come as no surprise that it is difficult to predict “species”-level composition of microbial communities. But natural microbial communities do have sufficiently stable functional properties to be effectively utilized by macroscopic organisms to accomplish definite tasks. This means that there should be some community-level quantities that are reproducible and controllable, and some “relevant variables” that reliably control them, but what these quantities could be remains an open question.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thermodynamic constraints in living matter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/thermodynamic-constraints" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thermodynamic constraints in living matter" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:04+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:04+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/thermodynamic-constraints</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/thermodynamic-constraints"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Arthur_Eddington">Sir Arthur Eddington</a> famously remarked that the Second Law of Thermodynamics holds “the supreme position among the laws of Nature.” Half a century earlier, <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Ludwig_Boltzmann">Ludwig Boltzmann</a> had already noted that thermodynamics constrains the activity of living systems, in such a way that the Darwinian “struggle for existence” could be framed in terms of entropy. Recent progress in non-equilibrium statistical mechanics has opened up new possibilities for fleshing out these insights, determining which features of biological activity are constrained by thermodynamic laws, and what the “negative entropy” obtained in the “struggle for existence” is used for.</p>

<p><a href="https://web.stanford.edu/group/prakash-lab/docs/Dumont2014-MBOC.pdf">One striking property</a> of living materials is their combination of mechanical strength and rapid adaptability. This combination is essential for effective locomotion and for autonomous damage repair, and is rarely found in inanimate systems. By characterizing this qualitative observation in terms of thermodynamic constraints, I have shown how the internal chemical potential differences maintained by cellular metabolism can give biological materials their special characteristics <a class="citation" href="#marsland2018active">(Marsland III &amp; England, 2018)</a>.</p>

<p>Thermodynamic consistency also places general bounds on the temporal precision of physical processes at finite temperature. One might expect that these constraints would affect the design of biochemical “clocks,” such as the KaiABC system that sets the circadian rhythm in a large class of photosynthetic bacteria. I ran simulations of the KaiABC system and used published data from experiments and other biochemical clock models to determine how close they came to the thermodynamic limit. I found that the precision of these biochemical processes was always at least an order of magnitude worse than the theoretical optimum, indicating that evolution somehow failed to fully optimize this figure of merit <a class="citation" href="#marsland2019thermodynamic">(Marsland III et al., 2019)</a>. Using a simplified toy model capturing the essential structure of the KaiABC system, I showed that the optimum could be achieved using a molecule with a sufficiently large number of sequentially accessed internal states, with comparable reaction rates for each internal step. This suggests that the sub-optimality of the clock precision is at least partially due to the difficulty of implementing such a large chemical cycle on a single molecule.</p>

<p>Alongside these specific projects, I have also authored or contributed to several general treatments of various aspects of non-equilibrium statistical mechanics, including <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1707.06680.pdf">a review article</a> providing an accessible introduction to some of the most important recent developments in the field <a class="citation" href="#marsland2015far">(Marsland III &amp; England, 2015; Marsland III, 2017; Perunov et al., 2016; Marsland III &amp; England, 2018)</a>.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="marsland2018active">Marsland III, R., &amp; England, J. L. (2018). Active regeneration unites high-and low-temperature features in cooperative self-assembly. <i>Physical Review E</i>, <i>98</i>(2), 022411.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.aps.org/pre/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevE.98.022411"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2018active-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.02172"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2018active-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2018active.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2019thermodynamic">Marsland III, R., Cui, W., &amp; Horowitz, J. M. (2019). The thermodynamic uncertainty relation in biochemical oscillations. <i>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</i>, <i>16</i>(154), 20190098.</span>

    
    <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/abs/10.1098/rsif.2019.0098"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019thermodynamic-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.00548"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2019thermodynamic-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2015far">Marsland III, R., &amp; England, J. (2015). Far-from-equilibrium distribution from near-steady-state work fluctuations. <i>Physical Review E</i>, <i>92</i>(5), 052120.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.aps.org/pre/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevE.92.052120"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2015far-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.00238"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2015far-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2015far.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2017edge">Marsland III, R. A. (2017). <i>The edge of thermodynamics: driven steady states in physics and biology</i> [PhD thesis]. Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</span>

    
    <a href="https://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/112008"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2017edge-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="perunov2016statistical">Perunov, N., Marsland, R. A., &amp; England, J. L. (2016). Statistical physics of adaptation. <i>Physical Review X</i>, <i>6</i>(2), 021036.</span>

    
    <a href="https://journals.aps.org/prx/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevX.6.021036"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_perunov2016statistical-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.1875"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_perunov2016statistical-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/perunov2016statistical.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="marsland2017limits">Marsland III, R., &amp; England, J. (2018). Limits of predictions in thermodynamic systems: a review. <i>Reports on Progress in Physics</i>, <i>81</i>(1), 016601.</span>

    
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6633/aa9101/pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2017limits-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.06680"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2017limits-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/marsland2017limits.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sir Arthur Eddington famously remarked that the Second Law of Thermodynamics holds “the supreme position among the laws of Nature.” Half a century earlier, Ludwig Boltzmann had already noted that thermodynamics constrains the activity of living systems, in such a way that the Darwinian “struggle for existence” could be framed in terms of entropy. Recent progress in non-equilibrium statistical mechanics has opened up new possibilities for fleshing out these insights, determining which features of biological activity are constrained by thermodynamic laws, and what the “negative entropy” obtained in the “struggle for existence” is used for.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conditions for emergence of self-sustaining metabolic networks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/emergence-metabolism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conditions for emergence of self-sustaining metabolic networks" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:03+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:03+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/emergence-of-metabolism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/emergence-metabolism"><![CDATA[<p>One of the distinctive features of living matter is the presence of self-sustaining metabolic reaction networks. Every time a cell divides, it must take in chemical compounds available in its environment, and use them to double the quantity of each internal molecular species. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autocatalytic_set">General properties of such collectively autocatalytic reaction networks</a> have been studied for many decades, but the rise of <a href="https://www.genome.jp/kegg/">biosphere-scale databases of biochemical reactions</a> has created new avenues for working out the necessary conditions for the spontaneous emergence of such networks.</p>

<p>My coauthors and I have shown how large and complex self-sustaining reaction networks could have spontaneously arisen in a variety of proposed pre-biotic geochemical scenarios, before the emergence of nitrogen-fixing or phosphate-fixing enzymes <a class="citation" href="#goldford2018boundary">(Goldford et al., 2019)</a>. I have been investigating the properties of collectively autocatalytic sub-networks in some of these scenarios, and am interested in applying methods from the physics of disordered systems to study the similarities and differences between these real sub-networks and the autocatalytic portions of random networks.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="goldford2018boundary">Goldford, J. E., Hartman, H., Marsland, R., &amp; Segrè, D. (2019). Environmental boundary conditions for the origin of life converge to an organo-sulfur metabolism. <i>Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution</i>, <i>3</i>, 1715.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-019-1018-8"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_goldford2018boundary-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/487660v1"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_goldford2018boundary-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    
    

    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the distinctive features of living matter is the presence of self-sustaining metabolic reaction networks. Every time a cell divides, it must take in chemical compounds available in its environment, and use them to double the quantity of each internal molecular species. General properties of such collectively autocatalytic reaction networks have been studied for many decades, but the rise of biosphere-scale databases of biochemical reactions has created new avenues for working out the necessary conditions for the spontaneous emergence of such networks.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mathematical tools for improving stem cell protocols</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-types" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathematical tools for improving stem cell protocols" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:02+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:02+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/cell-types</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-types"><![CDATA[<p>Induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSC’s) have generated considerable excitement for the future of regenerative medicine. Since these cells can be generated directly from readily accessible somatic patient cells, they can be used to grow new tissues and eventually organs with no risk of immune rejection. Coaxing the cells to differentiate into the desired tissue remains a major challenge, and the development of effective protocols is hampered by the fact that the success or failure of a given attempt is difficult to determine until the cells are delivered to a host.</p>

<p>Information about the cell type is already encoded in the gene expression levels as soon as the protocol is complete, however, and my colleagues have developed <a href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003734">a reliable method</a> for extracting this, based on the linear algebra of non-orthogonal projections. I have recently completed a project with <a href="https://ikonomoulab.com/">Laertis Ikonomou</a> and his colleagues at the BU Center for Regenerative Medicine, using this method to help develop protocols for generating lung cells <a class="citation" href="#ikonomou2020vivo">(Ikonomou et al., 2020)</a>.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="ikonomou2020vivo">Ikonomou, L., Herriges, M. J., Lewandowski, S. L., Marsland, R., Villacorta-Martin, C., Caballero, I. S., Frank, D. B., Sanghrajka, R. M., Dame, K., Kańduła, M. M., &amp; others. (2020). The in vivo genetic program of murine primordial lung epithelial progenitors. <i>Nature Communications</i>, <i>11</i>, 1.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-020-14348-3"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_ikonomou2020vivo-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/ikonomou2020vivo.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSC’s) have generated considerable excitement for the future of regenerative medicine. Since these cells can be generated directly from readily accessible somatic patient cells, they can be used to grow new tissues and eventually organs with no risk of immune rejection. Coaxing the cells to differentiate into the desired tissue remains a major challenge, and the development of effective protocols is hampered by the fact that the success or failure of a given attempt is difficult to determine until the cells are delivered to a host.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bayesian analysis for small molecule sensors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/bayesian-microscopy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bayesian analysis for small molecule sensors" /><published>2019-08-21T02:00:01+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T02:00:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/bayesian-microscopy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/bayesian-microscopy"><![CDATA[<p>The combination of gene editing and lattice light-sheet microscopy has opened a new era in cell biology. It is now possible, in principle, to fluorescently label any biologically relevant molecule and measure its dynamics across the whole cell in real time. Not only can proteins be labeled, by directly appending the code for a fluorescent domain to the gene of interest, but so can small molecules and ions, by hijacking the naturally occurring proteins that transduce information about their concentrations, using them to create artificial fluorescent probes. Stitching these sensors to other protein domains that specifically bind to different parts of the cell can provide additional spatial resolution, detecting even a small number of copies of the molecule of interest in the vicinity of a certain target structure. A number of small molecules such as cyclic AMP and phosophotidylinositol (PI) play crucial roles in signal transduction, and a complete understanding how the signal is processed requires careful measurements of their spatiotemporal dynamics in response to specific stimuli.</p>

<p>Inferring the dynamics of the molecules of interest from the observed behavior of the fluorescent probes, however, presents new challenges. The timescale of concentration changes for the target molecule is often comparable to the timescale for the probe to bind it, requiring a detailed kinetic model to back out the desired information. While it is usually straightforward to write down the kinetics for a well-characterized probe, the multi-domain molecules developed for the latest high-resolution measurements require a large number of unknown kinetic parameters, whose in vitro values do not necessarily reflect their behavior in the cytoplasm. Using these high-dimensional models correctly requires great care, because they easily give rise to “sloppy” directions in parameter space, which are unconstrained by the available data. I have developed some expertise in using Bayesian analysis to guide careful interpretation of the results of this kind of experiment, in the context of detecting phosphorylated PI molecules recruited to sites of clathrin-mediated endocytosis <a class="citation" href="#marsland2017edge">(Marsland III, 2017; He et al., 2017)</a>.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ol class="bibliography"><li><span id="marsland2017edge">Marsland III, R. A. (2017). <i>The edge of thermodynamics: driven steady states in physics and biology</i> [PhD thesis]. Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</span>

    
    <a href="https://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/112008"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_marsland2017edge-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    
    
    
    

    </li>
<li><span id="he2017dynamics">He, K., Marsland III, R., Upadhyayula, S., Song, E., Dang, S., Capraro, B. R., Wang, W., Skillern, W., Gaudin, R., Ma, M., &amp; others. (2017). Dynamics of phosphoinositide conversion in clathrin-mediated endocytic traffic. <i>Nature</i>, <i>552</i>(7685), 410.</span>

    
    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature25146"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_he2017dynamics-url" style="outline:none;">Journal</button></a>
    

    
    <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6263037/"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--BibTex" id="b_he2017dynamics-url" style="outline:none;">arXiv</button></a>
    
    
    
    <a href="/assets/repository/he2017dynamics.pdf"><button class="btn btnId btnPub--download" style="outline:none; position:relative;white-space: normal;">PDF</button></a>
    
    
    

    </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Robert A Marsland III</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The combination of gene editing and lattice light-sheet microscopy has opened a new era in cell biology. It is now possible, in principle, to fluorescently label any biologically relevant molecule and measure its dynamics across the whole cell in real time. Not only can proteins be labeled, by directly appending the code for a fluorescent domain to the gene of interest, but so can small molecules and ions, by hijacking the naturally occurring proteins that transduce information about their concentrations, using them to create artificial fluorescent probes. Stitching these sensors to other protein domains that specifically bind to different parts of the cell can provide additional spatial resolution, detecting even a small number of copies of the molecule of interest in the vicinity of a certain target structure. A number of small molecules such as cyclic AMP and phosophotidylinositol (PI) play crucial roles in signal transduction, and a complete understanding how the signal is processed requires careful measurements of their spatiotemporal dynamics in response to specific stimuli.]]></summary></entry></feed>